Okay,
let's continue with the story,
and then I'm going to take questions.
So let's see how long this
takes.
The three princes entered the
forest,
which was twelve levels deep, getting deeper and deeper.
And then they found a tigress,
a tigress lying
down, with
four tiger cubs. Excuse me,
no, it says she had
five cubs,
and the babies were very thin.
Five babies, five babies, excuse me.
And the eldest brother, Big Heart,
said, "This poor tigress
gave birth to these five
tiger cubs five or six days ago,
but she hasn't been able to find any
food this whole time. So it's
possible that if she gets too hungry, she'll eat
her cubs
or die."
The youngest prince, Big
Heart,
said to his brother, "Well, what does this kind
of animal eat?"
And the eldest brother said, "
Well, the food of tigers
and bears
and snowmen and abominable men. They
all eat the same thing. They like to eat
fresh meat, and they like blood."
Then the middle brother
said, "But
she's already very weak. She can't look for
food.
Someone should..."  Offering their bodies to
someone, who would do that?
The older brother said, "
That's too much for me to be asked to do
that."
The younger prince said, "
Well, you see, people like the three of us are too
attached to
our bodies,
and besides, we have very limited vision,
so it would be very difficult to give our
bodies to this tigress.
But if there were a person in this
forest
who was truly sage, they would
easily give their body to this
tigress.
If a true sage were
here,
even one who had
directly perceived emptiness, they would gladly give
their body
here."
So they decided to leave the tiger
and
returned to their parents. But
the younger brother kept
looking back at the
tigress. He didn't feel comfortable
having left.
[Music] He
thought to himself, "
The time has come. I must give my body.
Why have I had
this kind of body for
countless lifetimes?
This dirty body.
Inside it, we don't know if there's cancer or
not. We don't know. And many times I've
wasted this body,
and many times I've simply lost it
during many lifetimes, and I didn't do anything with
it.
And it's not going to survive this life,
so I should do something beautiful
with it.
If I..."  I offer my body, it's
as if it has become
a ship on the ocean. The ocean is
rebirth and death over and over again,
but if I offer my body, it will
become a ship, a vessel
that goes towards enlightenment. In
any case, this body is like
a bubble,
but a [ __ ] in Sanskrit, like the sutra, the
diamond cutter, like a bubble.
This body will not survive
in the end; the worms will enjoy it.
This is simply
a bag of poop and pee.
[Music]
If I offer this dirty body full of
poop and pee,
will I be able to obtain an immortal Buddha body
like a rainbow?
Then he said to his brothers, "You go
ahead." You know,
I forgot, I have something to do. I
have to go for a moment,
for a second."
So he turned around and went back to
the tigress. He
took off his clothes
and hung them on a tree branch. "
I will give this body, which is very difficult
to give, with wisdom,
with the understanding of the seeds, and
with love."
And then I will become a Buddha.
I want to be like a Bodhisattva,
and I want to obtain  The things that
bodhisattvas want to obtain,
and by doing this
I will escape the prison of this samsara.
And he said this prayer
[Music]
and then he lay down in front of the
tigress.
But the tigress was too weak to
do anything.
So he was there waiting,
and the tigress couldn't move.
And then he said, "Look, it's very sad." He
said, "She can't eat me like this."
Then he got up,
then broke off a sharp branch from a
tree and cut his neck,
this artery here.
And then he fell unconscious beside
the tigress.
At that moment,
the earth of this world
shook
like a small boat on the ocean
when there is a storm.
So in Buddhism we say that when
a bodhisattva does something very great,
the karma is very heavy and the earth
cannot support it,
and there will be an earthquake.
And also, there was an eclipse of the sun
[Music],
and there was no light
and the flowers began to fall from the sky.
Then one of the gods in the sky
said, "Wow, this person is amazing!"
and wrote him a poem: "
Your love covers all living beings,
and you have given your own life."
You want to obtain the form, the
greatest form of peace,
because of the karma of offering your body in such a
beautiful way.
You will definitely obtain these achievements
quickly.
Then
the tigers began to eat, and he could
see this body covered in blood,
and the tigress was able to easily devour it
until only the bones remained.
So the older brother asked the
middle brother
what was happening. Why was it
shaking like this?
Why was the earth shaking
like the ocean on a stormy day?
Why was the sunlight
blocked?
Why were flowers falling from the sky?
Our brother definitely gave
his body away.
[Music]
And I also think he had too much love. I
also think he gave his body away.
[Music]
And they were filled with sadness
and began to cry
and ran back
and arrived where the tigers were.
They saw all their brother's clothes
hanging on a tree, and then they saw
only bones,
and there was blood everywhere,
and hair around.
Then they were unconscious
on the bones. They lay there for a long time.
And you might be wondering if they were
eaten too. I was
wondering that too, but it seems the
tigress didn't.  I think the tigress, she was
satisfied,
and when they woke up,
they raised their hands to the sky
and screamed.
And also, our mother is going to ask
where our little brother is. It's
better if we both die right now. We can't
face our
mother.
How are our parents going to live
with this if they find out that we didn't stop it?
And they just sat there for about an
hour crying.
Then all the king's attendants
were looking for the princes. They were
looking everywhere.
Where are the boys? Where are
the boys?
[Music]
The mother was taking a nap, the
queen,
and she had several strange dreams
in which she lost something
she loved. She
dreamed that someone cut off both her breasts
and that her teeth fell out.
[Music]
She dreamed that she
found three very cute, very tiny baby doves,
three little scared doves, and
suddenly a hawk came, like a
very big eagle, and grabbed one of them and
flew away.
And then the earth shook, and she woke up.
Here's a poetic word for
oceans
because the man who sees the ocean...
I woke up because that's a
poetic word to talk about the ocean because it does
n't cover the earth
and because the sun has darkened,
the darkness of pain has reached my
heart.
[Music]
I'm trembling
and this man dreams about my breasts being
cut open. I'm afraid, I'm afraid
something bad happened to
my boys in the forest.
The king's attendants were still searching
the forest for the princes, but something
happened.
[Music]
So immediately she began to
cry. I
heard something.
I think we lost our beautiful son.
So the king's heart began to
beat rapidly and he began to feel like he was going crazy
and he said, "I think we lost
our most beautiful son."
[Music]
And then he said to his wife, the queen, "
Don't worry, I'll go myself. I'll
try to investigate what
happened."
And he found all these people
moving around in the forest looking for the
sons.
So the mother and father realized that
only two sons had
come out of the forest
and they realized that they had lost
a son. It's
the worst thing that can happen to a
person, to lose one of their children.
The worst thing in the world is...  To lose one of
your sons
or daughters,
and the greatest happiness is to have them
safe.
Then the queen cried out
[Music]
because I lost the youngest, the one I
loved the most.
And then they asked the other
two brothers what had happened.
They were so upset they couldn't
say anything. "
Tell me what happened," said the queen
[Music].
And the two boys explained what had
happened.
And the king and queen
went to see the place where the boy
had been killed
and found the bones without blood, without
flesh, and without tendons.
And they saw the son's hair everywhere,
and they fell like a tree
struck by a tornado.
Then the king's attendants
arrived with
water and lavender and
sprinkled it everywhere. "
The lord of death has come early
for one of my children.
Why didn't the lord of death come for
me first?"
[Music]
The mother began to scream, "
Who has destroyed
the lotus flower of my youngest son?
Of my youngest son?"
And she wrote a long poem.
Then they collected all the bones
and put them in one place
and built the stupa and placed the
bones inside.  At the stupa,
then Buddha finishes the story
and tells his disciple Ananda, "
Make them believe
that the tigress was someone else, but do
n't think so. It was me.
Excuse me, the prince was him.
I was the prince,
and those tiger cubs
became the first five
disciples.
When I was dying,
the prince said, '
If you eat from my body, then sign
a contract. After I become
a Buddha, you have to be my first
students, my first five
students.'
So that's the story of the tigress,
and those five
were in the first
teaching and the first turning of the Dharma.
The Buddha taught the Four Area Truths
in the first turning of the wheel. It's a
beautiful story, a very beautiful story. He
repeats it three times. He
taught the Four Area Truths three times.
Those five in the teaching,
during that same hour, the five
students perceived emptiness
directly.
Now we'll go back to hunger for a little while, and
then we'll do questions and answers.
And so, here we'll see how I teach the
Four Area Truths,
or monks.
This is the Area Truth of suffering.
This is the Area Truth of where it comes from.
This is the Area Truth
of having it. This is the Area Truth of
...
The method to stop it—
and now I'll make another point about
why they call it the Four Noble Truths—
was the Buddha's first teaching. All
our life is suffering. You
can go to courses on justice and
you can make money, find a beautiful partner,
have great health, have a
very peaceful mind,
but all of that you will lose.
Everyone loses it,
and it's amazing that we haven't
gone crazy. It's
amazing that we're trying to
make money or build a house or
have children.
Everyone is going to die. We're going to lose everything.
And after we die,
the children will die. Sometimes they die
before us.
And so, this is how our
life happens.
I get the impression that many
people ask, "Where are you going
next week?" I'm going to Thailand
because I'm going to a meditation course,
and people think you're a bit of a
hippie.
And they say, "Nothing, yeah, that's fine. Go on, you're not a
very serious person."
I am a serious person. I have a big
business. I have many offices. I have
a big house that we have to take
care of.
You're like a
meditating person. Yes, I had
a hippie meditating person, and well,
that sometimes makes you feel like a
person with low self-esteem, and you say, "Ah,
I'm not a..."  I'm such a big person, I don't
have much money,
I'm just passing the time in
Thailand. We
all have that perception of ourselves to some degree,
but in fact, there are
only 425 holy people
in the world right now,
sane people,
and everyone else is crazy.
You are trying to stop
death, you
are trying to stop pain in
this world.
Many people took
Bodhisattva vows today,
they made a commitment to try to
stop death in this world,
and maybe we are crazy,
and maybe there is no
way to stop
death,
but we are
smart enough to try,
and the rest of the world is a little... no. You
can look at them and say, no, you,
you are the one who is crazy.
If you don't go to Thailand, you are crazy.
I am not crazy,
in fact, you are crazy. This business of making a
big business
and more houses, more cars, and even a
beautiful family is blind. Have you
never read a newspaper? Do
n't you understand that you have to lose all
that, and the children too? You are going to
lose them, aren't you? Don't you
notice?
And I think that all the people who
are not in this room, in this room,
or in a similar room,
are actually a little crazy. I do
n't know, it's like their house is...  Imagine if their house were
on fire and they
were having a cappuccino,
or if I wanted a cappuccino that
was even better. Their house is
on fire and they're just saying, "
This cappuccino isn't that good,
I need a bigger one.
This one's good."
They're a little crazy.
That was the first teaching the Buddha
gave, the first truth: wake up,
just wake up. You're crazy! Have
n't you realized
that every generation before you has
died
and lost everything,
and yet you keep trying to
get things? What's wrong with you? That's
the first truth.
Second truth:
everything has a cause.
And there's a water leak in your
kitchen floor, a drip. I have a friend—well, no,
actually, that friend is me. I don't
want to admit it,
Nix, you know, because he helped me
fix it.
My ceiling started leaking,
and I don't know, maybe you're the same.
Sometimes I get lazy, maybe I did
n't do the fire offering
correctly, maybe I do
n't have the power to finish things
quickly,
and the ceiling is leaking
this year,
and I just look at it
and, God, or look, the ceiling is leaking, you know.
So I grab the mop and clean up
the water.
The truth is that  It doesn't rain much in
Arizona, it's good for lazy people,
and then it rains again, the roof is
leaking,
and I clean it again,
and I did that, I don't know how, for three months.
Nicky, where are you? Nick knows.
Then I finally said, "Ah, this is silly. I'm
going to clean the floor a hundred times. I should
find where
the leak is coming from,
and yet I'm too lazy to be something
smart and mechanical. You do
n't want to fix my roof, do you? I
'm an old man, I can't get up on the
roof. You're young."
And then I said, "Why is that?"
And he's definitely going to come
and fix it. He found the hole.
That's the second truth of the area:
find the hole, find the leak,
stop cleaning. Small problems are
never going to end.
Find the hole, that's
the second truth. Find the source,
the origin of the problems.
Next, and important,
was a great teaching. The first
teaching,
Doubt, sat in the first teaching
with five of his friends, his meditation friends,
and they were the five baby tigers. Right,
by the way, you can do it. It's a lot of
fun. Go to a McDonald's,
don't buy the hamburger, buy the
fries. Go outside if you're from
Schengen,
buy fries.  Go outside,
break them into small pieces and
throw them to the birds and say a
prayer. We
cannot give away our bodies, we
are not strong enough, but
we can give away fries. So break up
the fries and throw them to the
little birds, to the little birds,
and I say this prayer: If you eat my
fries, when I become
Buddha, you will be my first student. You
can do it, it's very fun. It's
a very correct way of thinking, a
very pure way of thinking.
So if you have a little free time,
you are hungry,
eat most of the fries,
but give yourself a little.
But play this Dharma game, say a
prayer: You are my first student,
you are my second,
and you can do it all the time. And it's
true, it's
really true.
When the Buddha met those five
people and gave his first teaching, it
was very radical
because of the third truth of the area. He
looked at his disciples and said, "You don't have to
die, you don't have to
die. I
know where the hole is, where
the leak is. I can teach you." It's a very
big thing.
If someone comes to your house and tells you, "You don't have to
die," you
would say, "How are you sure you
are a donation?" "Do you
want a..."  Donation?
No, they don't really have to die.
They have a feather,
but what is it?
We've never seen anyone in the newspaper
who hasn't died.
And the dogs had a meeting because
one dog said, "You can use this
to write." A
very intelligent dog, a Buddha among
the dogs,
explained to another dog, "
You can use this to communicate."
And they decided not to be crazy. They don't
have seeds to understand.
No, we've never seen anyone
use it to communicate.
This is just for biting. We've never seen anyone
who hasn't died,
therefore there is no one like that. Do you
understand?
They have the seed to see, a stick
to bite, and they say they don't exist. The
feathers are in their mouths.
There are people around them who haven't died, who haven't
died all day, but they can't
see them.
They have dog seeds, okay?
Don't say they don't exist just because you can't
see them.
That's truth number 3. Yes, you
can stop death. Yes, you can
stop death. And number 4,
there is a path. There is a way.
If you follow them, you do
n't have to die, okay?
That's the first teaching
for the five baby tigers. Baby tigers,
I have a suggestion.
Each of those truths has four
parts.
There are 16 parts about the Four Truths.
Nobody teaches them,
and I think nobody understands them. I'd
like to teach them to you,
but
tonight is a good time
for that. I'm going to teach them to you tonight.
So, my suggestion is to
take a
10-minute break. Some
people want to sign more books. Don't
worry, I'll do more tonight.
[Music]
But let's take a 10-minute
break for coffee and book signing. I
ask the teachers to stand at the
front and answer questions. A
10-minute break, and we'll be back. Okay,
here we go.
This is like a wedding cake, dessert
for you.
We're going to talk about the Four Truths.
In English, many years ago,
these Sanskrit words were translated as the
Four Truths.
The word "aria" was
translated as "noble."
Noble means a good person, like
a gentle person, like a gentleman,
a good person.
So, the first translators from
Sanskrit to English
didn't understand what "aria" meant.
So they wrote "Four Noble Truths."
These days, you can see it in English like this.
This became a very common translation,
but it's a poor translation of the
Sanskrit word "area."
So, they aren't four noble truths;
they're the four truths of the area.
What does "area" mean? "
Area" means... It's easy. Anyone who
has perceived emptiness directly...
If you perceive emptiness directly,
you're going to become a Buddha in a
short period of time, and you have no
choice. Even if you don't want to, you're going to
become a Buddha in a short
period of time.
So, what's the best way to see
emptiness?
What's the best way to become an
area quickly?
Start meditation in the air-
conditioned space,
and then
meditate on those four levels of
form, and then on those four levels of
formlessness. Bring your teacher to
mind,
which is the most powerful karma you can
do.
And then understand the emptiness of the false teacher.
The false teacher is the one who...  It doesn't come
from you.
It's like the fake husband in the kitchen.
What's his nickname? I didn't do
anything. He yelled at me. You
can call him
the husband, sir. I didn't do anything. I
just opened the door, and he yelled at me. I didn't do
anything.
This mind that I didn't do anything—
that's part of what we have to
cancel. The
teacher comes from you.
Every beautiful thing about them comes from you. Every
problem this
teacher has also comes from you. You
know,
this air conditioner,
the head touching—it comes from you too.
Everything comes from me. There isn't
a teacher I haven't
known in my past life,
and there isn't a teacher who won't
go with me to the afterlife.
This kind of teacher is fake. There's no such thing.
So you have to practice this
meditation many times. Now,
for us,
all parts of that meditation,
except for the part about the air
conditioner,
are pretending. We're just pretending
that we can reach the level of
form, that we can reach the level of
formlessness, that we can perceive
emptiness or see emptiness, that we can
see our past life. We can't do
any of that. It's very difficult to reach
even the first level of form,
and if you do a three-year retreat, maybe...
You reach the first realm of form, the
true one, or
do this meditation every day and
sow seeds, sow seeds,
sow seeds,
and you can do it at home. You do
n't have to leave for three years. You
would be three years older once you've been there since
the retreat, so it's not
necessary to do this meditation every
day.
And quickly, at level 9, you will see
emptiness.
At that moment, you become an area.
How long are you in meditation? It
lasts approximately 20 minutes. When you
come out—
I'm only referring
specifically to the part about
emptiness—in the restaurant, not in the
elevator,
after this you will quickly become a
Buddha. You have no choice; you
no longer have to die.
You can take care of your family forever,
and they can live with you
forever, and they won't die.
And all the irritating
little things from your family will
no longer be in your Buddha-nature. There will
only be pleasant things. Okay, so
why do we do the
lion dance?
We want to see emptiness directly.
When you perceive it directly, after
those 20 minutes, when you come out,
you are an area.
And this is like, "Wow, I did it!
I am an area!"
And the karma is so...  Powerful
that for one day many strange things
happen
many amazing things
those are the 16 parts of the Four
Truths
16 amazing things happen to you
4 in each truth
and you can see the names of the 16
but you can't find a
real explanation so we're going to do that
tonight
and that will be your special class
I'd like to say we have about 10 minutes if
you want to ask any questions you have
the microphone thank you
thank you for teaching and you are
a student
who comes often she has made me
many delicious dinners breakfasts
lunches all the time I
want to thank her
[Music]
she has made me gain a little weight thank you very much thank you
thank you for teaching
so we were having
dance classes at the retreat
and people seemed to enjoy them a
lot but many people were asking
why we have dance classes at a
hunger retreat
[Music]
and also the day we took
the vows for a day some
people were asking if they should dance
that day because they were wondering about
dance
so I was wondering if you could
explain a little bit about the purpose
of dance as a practice and with what
things  It has to do with the goals,
the goals of seeing the improvement directly
and things like that.
Okay, good question. I'll
tell you a nice story.
Before I did my three-year retreat, I did many, many
one-month
or two-month retreats.
And once, I was doing it in a
small cabin near the Grand
Canyon,
and it was going very well. The meditation was going
very well,
and one day I went outside, and there was a lot of smoke.
And if your meditation cabin is near
the forest, near a mountain, I
looked up at the top of the mountain, and there was
a very large fire.
The wind started to blow, and
the fire jumped from tree to tree without
touching the ground.
I didn't know, but later I found out, that
17 firefighters had
accidents that day near me, near
my meditation cabin.
They were fighting the fire, and the fire
caught them all. They all
ended up in the hospital. The
fire was moving very fast, approaching
very quickly.
And I was doing the
Kinder practice today and the Buddha Woman practice last
night, and I was doing this
mantra.
And those of you who have been to Damon
Mount at the retreat center, you
put up a sign.  special on your door,
on your window,
to protect
your cabin.
So I wondered if it
said there was mold and I should run, and the
answer was no, you shouldn't stay. And then
the fire started getting closer. So I
said maybe he's not right,
and maybe the mold is wrong.
So I grabbed my suitcase and started
running,
and I forgot my phone. I was very scared.
Then I got to the road
and hitched a ride to town,
and the fire burned everything around the area. I
was in a restaurant
and met some people. I met some
people, and I didn't have anything. I didn't have a
car or anything.
And they said, "You need a place to
stay,"
and I said yes, but I need it for a
month.
I'm doing a retreat. I'm on retreat." And they
said, "We have a barn where they
sometimes keep cows,
a very big building,
and if you want, you can stay there for a
month. The cows aren't there."
And I said yes, that sounds very good to me. It sounds very good to me. I'm
going to do it.
So I went to this barn
and was meditating
to rent a car because I wanted to get
my phone back
to see if it had burned.
And I went back to the meditation cabin,
and the owner who  That cabin challenged me. I was sitting
inside. The
whole forest burned for
miles
and never touched the cabin. It jumped over the
cabin. I was very happy and said, "Wang had
views. You Buddhists, you
Buddhists." I was very happy. He
said, "Those little things you put
on the doors, you have to teach me. You have to
teach me."
Only my case survived. I was very
happy. I
was happy too because my
phone was okay,
but the smell was very strong. The whole
forest burned, so I went to the barn,
and during meditation, I heard a voice
saying, "You're supposed to be here.
You were meant to be here."
Then I was supposed to
dance. At that point,
I was even more
fat. I
'm not a dancer, and I've never really
wanted to dance in my life. It's like, I don't like
yoga at all. I do
n't like jumping around. But
the voice was very clear,
and it told me, "
After the retreat is over, you must
dance for an hour
every day because it was a very, very
big place like this.
And then you must look for Eva."
And I said, "Who is Eva?" "
Don't worry, just look for her."
I looked for it,
and well, anyway, I started
dancing.
Then, when I got back to New York
from a talk at
Princeton University,
someone introduced me to this lady.
Her name is Bat Sheva, and I
said, "So, what do you do?"
And she said, "Princeton University
just opened a new department, and they
hired me to be the director of
that dance department." And I said, "
You're supposed to be teaching me?"
So I
said, "You're supposed to be
teaching me?" And she said, "Are you a
dancer?" And I said, "No, I don't know anything about
that."
And then I got another message that said I
should wear my monk's robes
during dance classes. So, the
first time I went to a class, I
told her I had to go to the bathroom,
and she said, "You have to pee." And I
said, "No, we have to change."
And she said, "Oh, you have dance clothes?" And I
said, "Yes." So I
put on my robes, and I came out, and
she looked at me with a
face of astonishment and said, "You're going to dance like that?"
And I said, "Sorry, I have to dance." And she
said, "Okay, okay."
[Music]
And I'm dancing with her  For several
years,
when I was taking
Eisai courses in New York (for seven years), I would go
dancing with her at night,
and I realized that this is a
wedding practice.
The chi, the energy, moves in a
very beautiful way, and it makes the Buddhas really
happy.
Last night, at the
fire ceremony, we did special dances.
One is called "energy," which means
dance. Dancing is a very beautiful offering,
and the Buddhas really like it,
so it's very good for your chi.
Energy
is a very beautiful offering, and the Buddhas
really like it. And when you start to get older,
when you grow up, you ca
n't jump as high anymore, and you can't
run as much,
but you can become more graceful,
like these older ladies doing
tai chi in the park.
The Buddhas really like it; they really
like these
older people who never stop dancing.
They like it a lot.
So, if you can, maybe do some
tai chi, do some dancing.
A good place to dance is your house.
Move the furniture, put on
some music, don't tell anyone,
just do it,
and it will be just you and the Buddha.
Sometimes it's very
beautiful. Well, we're going to stop
there. I'll see you again.  Let's
see at seven thirty and
we'll do 4